Agent client protocol or ACP has the
potential of becoming the new MCP. This
new protocol standardized communication
between code editors or idees and coding
agents. So what exactly is the problem
it's trying to solve? Every major
company is trying to release their own
CLI based coding agents. Now these CLI
based coding agents do have support for
some of the coding IDEs but in most
cases it's a hack rather than a native
support. This new protocol is trying to
standardize that. So you're going to be
able to see for example diffs in an IDE
that are made by the coding agent. Let
me show you this in action and later on
I'll show you why this is significant
and how does the protocol work. So this
is Zed an open-source IDE. It has
support for agent client protocol. So
right now it supports both cloud code
and Gemini CLA and they are adding
support for new agents. So let's say if
we select Gemini CLI you're going to see
that it acts very similar to a simple
coding agent for example that present in
cursor. You don't really see any other
CLI based tool anymore. And let's ask it
create a Python file that implements AAR
search algorithm.
Now when you send the command, it feels
like you are just interacting directly
within the IDE. The beauty of agent
client protocol is that it is IDE and
agent agnostic. So any IDE that is going
to support or add support for this
protocol will act in exactly the same
way. So here Gemini CLI came up with a
code we are going to allow for it to
edit and in here you see that it created
a new Python file but you can actually
see all the diffs directly within the
IDE. Now Gemini CLI has support for VS
code where you can integrate it Gemini
CLI and then you see the diffs in VS
code but it's not universal but the goal
or the idea behind this protocol is that
it's going to become universal. Let's
say we accept all these changes but now
we want to continue working on this file
but we want to use clot code instead. So
here I can just click on clot code. it
is going to create another thread within
the same IDE. And now I can say add
comments to and the rest of the
functionality works in a similar way
that works in cloud code. So we can just
reference to a specific file. We're
going to send in the request and cloud
code would be able to make updates to
the file. Again, it's asking us for
permission. So we're going to allow it.
And you can actually see all the diffs
directly within IDE again. So there's a
very tight integration between the IDE
and coding agent through agent client
protocol. Again, it's agnostic to both
the coding agent and the IDE. And that's
the beauty because even though if there
is a support for cloud code in curs,
it's a hack that Entropic had to
implement. But now in this case, the
communication is going to be
standardized. Okay. So who is behind
this? This protocol was created by Zed
Industries who are also the creators of
Zed IDE. That's the opensource
coding integrated development
environment that we saw in conjunction
with the Google Gemini team. So at the
moment it supports Gemini CLI and cloud
code out of the box. If you run it for
the first time you will have to log in
but it also has the ability to support
any other custom agents as well. In that
case, you will need to just create a
JSON file with this specific structure.
So, you're going to have the agent
server, then what exactly the command
it's going to use, and then there is a
an index.js file which is going to point
to that specific agent. And the beauty
is that it's an open- source protocol.
So hopefully more players will get
involved and make this protocol better.
But the idea is that we want to minimize
integration overhead. So right now every
new a agent editor combination requires
custom work with this protocol. Similar
to MCP you take that away and also agent
work with only limited number of
available editors that we have seen a
cursor does not have support for all of
the coding agents. Same is the case with
VS code and windsurf. And also sometimes
there are developer loginins. So
choosing an agent often means accepting
their available interfaces. But with ACP
you take that away. Now you can
potentially integrate any coding agent
within the IDE of your choice. So a code
editor can talk to any agent through
standard IO. So what exactly is this
under the hood? It's a JSON RCP protocol
that lets any code editor talk to any
coding agent. So you can just plug and
play and the idea is that it takes away
friction. So the editor with the first
class UI to the coding agent that means
you'll be able to see live divs,
multibuffer reviews, navigation and
everything. Here's a very simple
architecture. So you have the client
that is your code editor and then on the
other side you have the agent very
similar to the MCP protocol. Once the
communication is established between the
two then the code editor is being
controlled by the coding agent. Here's a
more detailed flow. So this is transport
agnostic. You use commonly standard
input output operations uh to a
subprocess. The editor starts the agent
and exchange structured request and
responses and then the agent proposes
actions that will be navigate, edit, run
tool etc. Now you might be thinking how
exactly is this different from MCP. Uh
so ACP controls the communication
between the editor and coding agent.
That means that it gives the agent the
ability to control uh UI components or
control channels. For example, edit
navigation, reviews, diffs, those are
directly the communication between the
agent and the editor. On the other hand,
MCP is agent and tool communication. So,
it's a standard way to expose tools or
context to your agent. So, essentially
they are complimentary and ACP editor
can let an ACP agent use MCP server
under editor mandated per permissions.
Right? So there is absolutely no
conflict. Essentially you're just adding
communication between the editor and
code coding agent which is agnostic of
the both. Keep in mind these are early
specs so it's actively evolving. Expect
changes and there are going to be
versioning. At the moment it's written
in Rust. The whole Z IDE is written in
Rust. So we'll have to see if the other
coding agents plus the editors are going
to add support for this or not. Now
another very important thing to consider
is the security and authentication
aspect. MCP still struggle with that. I
haven't really seen much on ACP either.
So at the moment it's only available in
Z IDE which is an open source model. So
if you use claude or Gemini CLI, I think
it's a pretty good coding editor because
you can run it for free. They also have
their own coding agent. So if you go
open a new thread, you can select a
number of different models including
some of the open weight models that are
running on Olama on your machine. For
example, you can actually see them here.
But instead of I guess paying for that,
I would either use clot code or Gemini
CLA. if you have already subscription.
Anyways, do let me know your thoughts of
what you think about ACP. I'd highly
recommend to at least read about this
because this could be as big as MCP.
Thanks for watching and as always, see
you in the next one.